Guide to the New-York Historical Society Museum Department Records 1765, 1830-2018 NYHS-RG 20
New-York Historical Society
- Series IV. Collection Management Files, 1929-2008; 36.93 Linear feet
  - Subseries IV.C. Albina De Meio and Related Files, 1979-1994, 1999; 2.74 Linear feet
    - Storage & Warehousing, circa 1990 (Offsite-box 312)
      Includes files related to the move to Crozier. Includes contract and floor plan blueprints.
    - Labels (2 folders), Undated (Offsite-box 148, Folder 11-12)
      Includes various labels from the "vault" and the "gun closet."
    - Custody Receipts (24 folders), 1987-1992 (Offsite-box 149, Folder 1-24)
      Includes files on objects left with N-YHS for consideration of accepting it for the collection. Most indicate the object was declined, but some were accessioned.
    - Collections Use & Access (16 folders), 1989-1994 (Offsite-box 149, Folder 25-40)
      Includes files related to exhibitions, special events, and researcher access. No specific exhibition is represented here in any depth.
    - Collection Management Guidelines, circa 1993, 1999 (Offsite-box 150, Folder 1)
      Includes a binder (now disbound) of policy and procedure documents. The binder dated from the early 1990s, but inside the front cover was a 1999 procedure for numbering objects.
    - Jewish Museum (4 folders), 1989-1991 (Offsite-box 150, Folder 2-5)
    - Administration (9 folders), 1989-1994 (Offsite-box 150, Folder 6-14)
      Includes arrangements of office equipment, including computers, and various schematic floor plans.
  - Subseries IV.D. Luce Center Logistics, 1993, 1998-2001; 1.54 Linear feet
    The subseries appears to be a mix of files from various individuals involved with the logistics of establishing the Henry Luce III Center for the Study of American Culture, which opened in 2000, including project manager Leslie Davol, Nancy Rosoff, researcher Jennifer Jensen, and perhaps others. The subject matter includes environmental considerations for the Luce Center, such as HVAC and lighting, arrangements for packing and transport of objects from the Crozier warehouse to the Center, and preliminary object descriptions and location mapping.
    The subseries is arranged by general subject categories. The categories were defined by the processing archivist in order to simplify and summarize the presentation of the individual folders in the subseries. The archivist developed the categories based on observation of the relationship of groups of folders within the original storage boxes. Although the archivist did make some adjustments to their arrangement, in large part the folders found together remain that way.
    - Warehousing (4 folders), 1999-2000 (Offsite-box 151, Folder 1-4)
      Includes documents related to arrangements for the transfer of objects from the off-site Crozier warehouse to the Luce center and elsewhere. Includes N-YHS's "Guidelines for Handling Collections" (2000).
    - Warehousing (4 folders), 1999 (Offsite-box 287)
      Includes documents related to arrangements for the transfer of objects from the off-site Crozier warehouse to the Luce center and elsewhere.
    - Luce Center Construction (6 folders), 1993, 1998-2000 (Offsite-box 151, Folder 5-10)
      Includes documents concerning planning for lighting, HVAC, wall paint, and other environmental matters. Includes a copy of the 1993 building feasibility study, with notes, by the architects Beyer Blinder Belle and others.
    - Object Location Mapping & Text (16 folders), 1999-2000 (Offsite-box 152, Folder 1-16)
      Includes preliminary drafts of descriptive texts for some objects and lists and diagrams indicating proposed locations for objects in the Luce Center.
    - Object Location Mapping (4 folders), 2000? (Offsite-box 153, Folder 1-4)
      Includes the disbound contents of a binder concerning the location mapping for objects in the Luce Center.
    - Object Location Mapping, 2000-2002 (Offsite-box 304)
  - Subseries IV.E. Conservation Surveys and Other Files, 1977-2007; 2 Linear feet
    The subseries includes records that have a specific focus on conservation of the collections and particular objects, especially surveys and other standalone files transferred to the archives by the museum's conservators. (Conservation-related files that were found in the context of curatorial, exhibition, or other file sets are found there.)
    The subseries is arranged roughly by chronology and subject.
    - Paintings Conservation. Images and Exhibition (2 folders), 1977-1978 (Offsite-box 287)
      Includes slides of paintings by Thomas Cole, William Beekman, and Thomas Sully, and related conservation details. Includes snapshots of gallery installation.
    - Various Conservation Files (Richard Gallerani Files?) (9 folders), 1988-1995 (Offsite-box 287)
      Topics include: silver conservation survey (1990); list of loans to Gracie Mansion (1990); buildings renovation notes from a conservation perspective (1992-94); sculpture survey (1990); paintings conservation for the Thomas Hiram Hotchkiss exhibition (1989-1993); Mickey Mouse advertisement from the Bella Landauer collection (1994); some paintings conservation cards (circa 1988); photos of saddle bags, before and after treatment (1995); and color slides of various sculptures.
    - Outgoing Loan Files (Richard Gallerani Files?) (30 folders), 1991-1995 (Offsite-box 303)
    - Furniture Survey (6 folders), 1990s? (Offsite-box 287)
    - Treated Miniatures, 1991 (Offsite-box 303)
      Includes binder of lists by accession number of treated miniatures, with photographic contact sheets and negatives of the objects, and removed labels with identifying notations, etc.
    - Collections Survey, circa 1991 (Offsite-box 303)
      Small binder of reports on: new study/storage facilities for paintings, sculpture and decorative arts; silver; furniture; sculpture; and architectural collections.
    - Textile Survey (17 folders), 1995-1997 (Offsite-box 286)
      Survey performed by The Textile Conservation Workshop, funded by the Institute of Museum Services. Object level reports and photographs. Includes printed textiles, scarves, kerchiefs, beadwork, samplers, needlework, rugs, tablecloths, wall hangings, clothing, afghan, bed coverings, coverlets, flags, banners, Masonic, etc.
    - Conservation/cataloging worksheets, 1998-1999 (Offsite-box 287)
      Includes Collections Cataloging Worksheets and Multi-MIMSY summary reports for various artworks (furniture, toys, ceramics, textiles, personal accessories, etc.) Includes color photographs (Polaroids)of objects stapled to worksheets.
    - Painting glazing project (1 folder), 2007 (Offsite-box 287)
  - Subseries IV.F. Incoming Loan and Other Exhibition-Related Files, 1980-2007; 4.55 Linear feet
    The subseries includes exhibition records that were transferred to the archives, generally from the Registrar/Collections Management unit, rather than the Curatorial are other museum units. These generally concern incoming loans, object movement and safekeeping, and other matters within the broad purview of Collections Management.
    The subseries was created in 2021 to accomodate transfers received after the 2016 archives processing project. The files largely remain as received from the Museum and are described broadly.
    - That Belmont Look, 1980 (Offsite-box 294)
    - Tiffany Silver, 1980 (Offsite-box 294)
    - A Remnant in the Wilderness: New York Dutch Scripture Paintings, 1980 (Offsite-box 294)
    - Small Folk, 1980-1981 (Offsite-box 294)
    - Oom Pah Pah: The Great American Band, 1982 (Offsite-box 293)
    - Oom Pah Pah: The Great American Band, 1982 (Offsite-box 294)
    - The Stature of Liberty: America's Symbol of Freedom in Artists' Views, 1985-1986 (Offsite-box 294)
    - Baroness Hyde de Neuville: Sketches of America, 1984 (Offsite-box 294)
    - Lost in the Shuffle, 1984-1985 (Offsite-box 294)
    - Pageant of Heraldry in Britain & America, 1984 (Offsite-box 313)
    - New York & the China Trade, 1984 (Offsite-box 313)
    - Centuries of Childhood, 1985 (Offsite-box 313)
    - Karol Kozlowski, 1985 (Offsite-box 313)
    - Niagara, 1986 (Offsite-box 313)
    - James Henry Cafferty, 1986 (Offsite-box 312)
    - Various exhibitions, 1996-2007 (Offsite-box 311)
      The box holds incoming loan files of many exhibitions: Murders that Changed New York; Heny James; Treasures from Mt. Vernon; George B. Post; William Sydney Mount; Unconventional Currier & Ives; To Hell with Reform; Celebrated Hatter; New York City Ballet (largest set in box); $24 Deal; Uncle Sam; Flophouse; Building on the Flatiron; The Rosenbergs; Seat of Empire; Manhattan Unfurled; Angry Dove; Kid City; Victoria Woodhull; Eleanor Roosevelt.
  - Subseries IV.G. General Collections Management Files, 1980s-2008; 4.05 Linear feet
    - Various files, 1980s-1990s (Offsite-box 288)
      Includes various files transferred to the archives in 2019, described by the museum as: "Records include New York Times articles about New-York Historical Society financial crisis in the 1990's, emergency planning handbooks, insurance documents for disaster planning, correspondence about art insurance coverage, letters outlining N-YHS temporary holding letters, capital campaign project documents, correspondence about research of collections, speakers lists from Gilder Lehrman Collection, and acquisition worksheets." additional Museum records transferred at the time are also in the box including: registrar reports (circa 1986) and a few exhibition files (especially watercolors (1984).
    - Collection Management Guidelines and Procedures Manual, circa 1990 (Offsite-box 303)
    - Various files, 1990s-2002 (Offsite-box 314)
      This box was transferred by the museum to the archives in 2020. It includes a mix of files that appear to have come from the files of various collections management staff including Jack Rutland, Margaret Tamulonis, Albina deMeio, Kimberly Terbush, Janice Dockery, and others. The files relate to loans, the Treasures reinstallation, acquisitions (including original 1998 gift agreement for the Emma Thursby portrait by Healy), photographs of objects destroyed according to procedure (1999), affidavits concerning subway photographs ownership (1995), and various other matters.
    - Grants for Conservation and Digitization, 1987-2004 (Offsite-box 305)
      Includes various files transferred to the archives from the museum in 2019, which described the files as: "Records include correspondence and reports for museum grants between the years 1987-2004. The majority of the grants are for conservation programs for paintings and watercolors for N-YHS collections, but some grants involve digitization projects and updates to collections management policies. Types of records included are grant reports, emails and correspondence, CV's of relevant personnel. Also included are invoices of individual conservators.'
    - Collections Management Policies and Projects, circa 1987-2008 (Offsite-box 306)
      Includes records transferred to the archives by the museum in 2019. The museum described the content as: "Records include acquisition proposals, deaccession reports, and reviews of potential acquisitions. Includes collections management policies for special events, art handling, and the Decorative Arts Department; documents on conservation projects such as textile rolling and storage are present as well."
- Series V. Catalogues, Inventories, Surveys, 1830-2000; 12.25 Linear feet
  The series includes a wide variety of miscellaneous catalogues, inventories, and other documents related to object descriptions. These range from John Delafield's 1830 handwritten inventory of the ancient coins and medals in the N-YHS "cabinet" to the user manual for the Multi-MIMSY 2000 System, N-YHS's collection management system at the turn of the twenty-first century. The series also holds the annotated and edited manuscripts of three catalogues published in the 1970s-1980s of N-YHS's American paintings (by Richard J. Koke and by Wayne Craven) and glass paperweights (by Paul Hollister). The container list includes a complete list of the specific contents.
  The material in the collection was compiled together into the series by the processing archivist. The series is arranged in chronological order.
  - J. Delafield's Inventory of N-YHS's Coins & Medals, 1830 (Box 154, Folder 1)
  - Printed Lists Likely Related to Coin Inventory (5 folders), circa 1830? (Box 154, Folder 2-6)
  - Catalogue of the N-YHS Museum & Gallery of Art, 1866 (Box 154, Folder 7)
  - "Champlain's Astrolabe", 1879 (Box 154, Folder 8)
    Includes typescript concerning the astrolabe written by A.J. Russell. Also includes a reprint from the N-YHS Quarterly Bulletin of George Zabriskie's article "A Story of Astrolabes."
  - Catalogue of the N-YHS Museum & Gallery of Art, 1903 (Box 154, Folder 9)
  - Description of the Cabinet of Coins & Medals of John C. Kunze, Undated (Box 154, Folder 10)
    Includes handwritten notes of drawer contents, possibly a copy of a printed description.
  - "Inventory of the Jenny Lind Collection" by Leonidas Westervelt, circa 1945 (Box 154, Folder 11)
  - Checklist of N-YHS Sculpture & Medals, circa 1970? (Box 154, Folder 12)
  - Catalogue of American Portraits in the New-York Historical Society. Correspondence and Additional Entry Research (10 folders), 1959-1979 (Offsite-box 157, Folder 1-10)
    These folders include correspondence and some research notes related to the production of Catalogue of American Portraits in the New-York Historical Society, published in 1974 by Yale University Press. Wayne Craven was the author of the original manuscript, which was published after extensive further research and editing at N-YHS by Wendy Shadwell, Robert Strunsky, and Librarian James Gregory.
  - Catalogue of American Portraits in the New-York Historical Society (17 of 47 folders), circa 1970 (Offsite-box 158, Folder 1-17)
    This record carton and the next two Includes Wayne Craven's manuscript for this book with further research notes and edits by Wendy Shadwell and others. The documents remain in their original folders.
  - Catalogue of American Portraits in the New-York Historical Society (21 of 47 folders), circa 1970 (Offsite-box 159, Folder 1-21)
  - Catalogue of American Portraits in the New-York Historical Society (9 of 47 folders), circa 1970 (Offsite-box 160, Folder 1-9)
  - Glass Paperweights of the New-York Historical Society, circa 1974 (Offsite-box 160, Folder 10-19)
    Includes edited, draft typescripts of Paul Hollister's book, published in 1974.
  - Glass Paperweights of the New-York Historical Society, circa 1974 (Offsite-box 160, Cards -)
    Includes index cards with descriptive information for the illustrations, glossary, etc. from the book.
  - Randall J. Le Boeuf, Jr. Catalogue of his Robert Fulton Collection (1 of 2), circa 1970s (Offsite-box 302)
    4 of 7 binders of Le Boeuf's original, annotated catalogue, covering both library and museum materials. This box holds Volumes I and II of "ALS [autograph letter signed] and other original MS [manuscript] material"; a volume of Steamboats, America and Foreign; and a volume on "Pictures," meaning "paintings, photos, engravings, prints." This last volume has an overview, dated 1976, of the entire catalogue.
  - Randall J. Le Boeuf, Jr. Catalogue of his Robert Fulton Collection (2 of 2), circa 1970s (Offsite-box 303)
    Includes 3 of 7 binders, including the three volumes covering "books, newspapers, pamphlets."
  - American Landscape and Genre Paintings in the New-York Historical Society (Box 1 of 4), circa 1982 (Offsite-box 307, Volume 1-5)
    These 4 boxes hold 2 copies of the annotated and edited typescript for Richard J. Koke's American Landscape and Genre Paintings in the New-York Historical Society: A Catalog of the Collection, Including Historical, Narrative, and Marine Art, published in 1982. The first set consists of 13 volumes of photocopies. The second set is an incomplete 11 volume set. Although both the sets are photocopies, the second copy is marked as the original. Also there appears to be some original edits in the second set that do not appear in the first set. This first box holds set 1, volumes 1-5.
  - American Landscape and Genre Paintings in the New-York Historical Society (Box 2 of 4), circa 1982 (Offsite-box 308, Volume 6-11)
    This box holds set 1, volumes 6-11.
  - American Landscape and Genre Paintings in the New-York Historical Society (Box 3 of 4), circa 1982 (Offsite-box 309)
    This box holds set 1, volumes 12-13, and set 2, numbered as volumes 14-17.
  - American Landscape and Genre Paintings in the New-York Historical Society (Box 4 of 4), circa 1982 (Offsite-box 310)
    This box holds set 2, volumes 18-23.
  - Swords, 1987 (Offsite-box 304)
    Two binders of object descriptions.
  - Waldron Phoenix Belknap, Jr. Collection, circa 1988? (Box 154, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous Loose Tags, Labels, etc., circa 1865-1909 (Box 154, Folder 14)
  - Museum Collections Workbook (2 copies) (4 folders), circa 1991 (Offsite-box 155, Folder 1-4)
  - Multi-MIMSY 2000 Book. Activities (2 folders), 1997 October (Offsite-box 155, Folder 5-6)
  - Multi-MIMSY 2000. Implementation Manual (Draft), 1998 January (Offsite-box 155, Folder 7)
    Includes system installation and upgrade CDs.
  - Multi-MIMSY 2000 Book. (4 manuals/folders), 1999 (Offsite-box 156, Folder 1-4)
  - Multi-MIMSY 2000. Vocabulary List Reports (Offsite-box 156, Folder 5-7)
  - Index cards to reference materials, undated (Offsite-box 301)
    Csrds arranged by chronology and subject pointing to research resources, such as books, photos, etc., at least some of which are in N-YHS collections.
- Series VI. Object Images, 1765, circa 1864-circa 1990; 23.96 Linear feet in 23 document boxes and cartons, and 13 small boxes of slides
  The series includes the museum's photograph files for select objects, which generally appears to be paintings, drawings and sculpture. The photograph files also hold some other documents, such as correspondence related to acquisitions, research notes, inquiries, and other matters. The series also holds a set of negatives for the Stuart collection, lantern slides of the works of American and European artists, and photographs of the Grider, Catlin and Dunsmore drawings.
  The series is organized in two subseries:
  Subseries VI.A. Image Files
  Subseries VI.B. Sets of Images
  - Subseries VI.A. Image Files, 1765, circa 1864-circa 1990; 8.25 Linear feet
    The series includes the museum's photograph files for select objects, which generally appears to be paintings, drawings, and some sculpture. The series retains the original folders, which include the object/accession number, the negative number of the object's image and, for some, other notes. For the bulk of the folders, the content includes only one or two black and white photographic prints. Many of the folders hold no documents, but those empty folders were also retained in the series.
    In addition to photographs, a considerable number of folders also include other documents. These documents concern the object's acquisition, attributions, research notes on the object's subject, inquiries from outside N-YHS about the object, conservation/restoration reports, deaccession in some cases, and other matter. A small number of these additional documents are exceptional, such as the original 1765 declaration of John Cruger naming Joseph Drake a freeman and citizen of New York City (object 1957.64) and Frederic De Peyster's 1864 letter presenting the drawing by John J. Audubon of John Cleeves Symmes to N-YHS (object 1864.4). Also, some files include a negative or transparency (often color) of the object. During processing, the archivist attempted on a time limited best efforts basis to identify which files held documents other than black and white prints and these instances are noted in the container list below; researchers should not rely exclusively on these notes as other files may well hold useful documentation, such as descriptions written on the back of photographs.
    The series follows the original order of the files, which includes three sets, each of which is in object number order. The first set includes objects related to boats or ships. The second set, which is the bulk of the series, includes objects other than boats or ships. The third set includes a small number of loaned objects.
    - Boats or Ships. x.160 - x.281 (Offsite-box 161, Folder -)
    - Boats or Ships. 1899.1 - 1947.66 (Offsite-box 161, Folder -)
      Includes restoration notes (1924.102, 1924.120, 1936.806, 1938.410, 1938.411, 1938.413, 1938.415, 1941.926, 1942.248); correspondence/notes (1924.111, 1925.107, 1926.76, 1947.66).
    - Boats or Ships. 1948.485 - 1981.14 (Offsite-box 162, Folder -)
      Includes restoration notes (1948.488); correspondence/notes (1948.486, 1950.292, 1954.167).
    - 1816.1 - 1867.391 (Offsite-box 162, Folder -)
      Includes restoration notes (1818.1,1854.1, 1856.3, 1863.10, 1867.298, 1867.306); correspondence/notes (1816.1, 1816.2, 1817.1, 1817.6, 1817.10, 1854.1, 1857.7, 1860.90, 1860.91, 1860.96, 1862.5, 1864.1, 1864.4, 1867.294, 1867.301); negatives/transparencies (1867.294, 1867.298, 1867.302, 1867.306, 1867.312). Includes the original April 5, 1864, letter from Frederic De Peyster describing and presenting the drawing by John J. Audubon of John Cleeves Symmes to N-YHS (object 1864.4).
    - 1867.392 - 1899.7 (Offsite-box 163, Folder -)
      Includes restoration notes (1867.438, 1871.1, 1887.6, 1897.1); correspondence/notes (1873.4, 1874.2, 1881.21, 1881.22, 1887.8, 1895.8, 1896.2); negatives/transparencies (1873.4, 1880.10, 1887.6); slides (1873.5 to 1873.19).
    - 1900.7 - 1910.62 (Offsite-box 164, Folder -)
      Includes restoration notes (1905.292, 1907.3, 1908.8, 1909.20, 1910.5); correspondence/notes (1900.7, 1903.3, 1903.13, 1904.1, 1904.36, 1905.184, 1906.2, 1906.4, 1907.7, 1907.32, 1907.10, 1908.2, 1909.14, 1909.26, 1910.12, 1910.23, 1910.47); negatives/transparencies (1906.4, 1907.10, 1909.16, 1910.8); slides (1904.1).
    - 1911.2 - 1921.118 (Offsite-box 165, Folder -)
      Includes restoration notes (1918.6, 1918.16, 1918.17, 1920.4, 1921.11); correspondence/notes (1911.24, 1912.5, 1915.1. 1915.7, 1917.3, 1920.4); negatives/transparencies (1918.6, 1920.150, 1921.108).
    - 1922.6 - 1925.196 (Offsite-box 166, Folder -)
      Includes restoration notes (1925.5, 1925.14); correspondence/notes (1923.10, 1923.161 A + B, 1924.11, 1925.177, 1925.29a, 1925.100, 1925.177); negatives/transparencies (1923.5, 1923.137, 1923.138).
    - 1926.2 - 1935.59 (Offsite-box 167, Folder -)
      Includes restoration notes (1929.26, 1930.2, 1932.4); correspondence/notes (1931.4, 1932.10, 1932.16, 1932.237, 1933.4, 1933.8, 1934.5, 1934.11, 1934.13, 1934.14, 1935.30); negatives/transparencies (1930.2, 1932.21, 1932.23, 1933.8).
    - 1935.78 - 1936.1016 (Offsite-box 168, Folder -)
      Includes restoration notes (1935.98, 1936.404, 1936.799); correspondence/notes (1935.87, 1935.92, 1935.101, 1936.799); negatives/transparencies (1935.157).
    - 1937.36 - 1941.481 (Offsite-box 169, Folder -)
      Includes restoration notes (1937.162, 1937.450, 1940.76, 1940.451, 1941.240, 1941.269, 1941.363, 1941.425); correspondence/notes (1937.451, 1937.583, 1937.1718, 1937.1721, 1938.316, 1938.350, 1939.11, 1940.463, 1940.486; 1940.971, 1941.93, 1941.132, 1941.133, 1941.136, 1941.241, 1941.363); negatives/transparencies (1937.138, 1937.1805, 1939.11, 1939.243, 1939.244, 1940.451). Includes documents regarding the estate settlement of Elizabeth B. Knight (1940.350).
    - 1941.640 - 1944.392 to .428 (Offsite-box 170, Folder -)